ⓘ These English & Foreign subtitles created by ZoowlCZ (ver. 2024-10) are an expanded version of the English subtitles (5581877) uploaded by lusiads to OpenSubtitles.
It's true, you don't see many Dwarf women.
And in fact, they are so alike
in voice and appearance...
that they're often mistaken for Dwarf men.
It's the beards.
This, in turn, has given rise to the belief...
that there are no Dwarf women...
and that Dwarves just spring
out of holes in the ground...
which is, of course, ridiculous.
It's all right. Nobody panic.
That was deliberate. It was deliberate.
I haven't seen my niece smile for a long time.
She was a girl when they brought her father back dead.
Cut down by Orcs.
She watched her mother succumb to grief.
Then she was left alone, to
tend her king in growing fear.
Doomed to wait upon an old man who
should have loved her as a father.
Gimli.
No, I couldn't
I really couldn't.
I made some stew.
It isn't much, but it's hot.
Thank you.
- It's good.
- Really?
My uncle told me a strange thing.
He said that you rode to war
with Thengel, my grandfather.
But he must be mistaken.
King Theoden has a good memory. He
was only a small child at the time.
Then you must be at least 60.
Seventy?
But you cannot be 80!
Eighty-seven.
You are one of the Dunedain.
A descendant of Numenor, blessed with long life.
It was said that your race had passed into legend.
There are few of us left.
The Northern Kingdom was destroyed long ago.
I'm sorry. Please, eat.
The light of the Evenstar does not wax and wane.
It is mine to give to whom I will.
Like my heart.
Go to sleep.
[Sindarin] ♫ Ú i vethed... ♫
♫ [English]  ♫ Not the end... ♫
I am asleep.
This is a dream.
Then it is a good dream.
[Sindarin] ♫ ...nâ i onnad. ♫
♫ [English]  ♫ ...it is the beginning. ♫
Sleep.
[Sindarin] Minlû pedich nin...
[English] Once you told me...
[Sindarin] ...i aur hen telitha.
[English] ...this day will-come.
[Sindarin] Ú i vethed... nâ i onnad.
[English] Not the end... it is the beginning.
[Sindarin] Boe bedich go Frodo.
[English] It is necessary you go with Frodo.
[Sindarin] Han bâd lîn.
It is your path.
[Sindarin] Dolen i vâd o nin.
[English] Hidden the path is from me.
[Sindarin] Si peliannen i vâd na dail lîn.
[English] The way is already spread before your feet.
[Sindarin] Si boe ú-dhannathach.
[English] Now it-is-necessary you-don’t-fall.
Arwen...
[Sindarin] Ae ú-esteliach nad...
[English] If you trust not things...
[Sindarin] ...estelio han...
[English] ...trust this...
[Sindarin] ...estelio ammen.
[English] ...trust us.
[Sindarin] ♫ Estelio han. ♫
♫ [English]  ♫ Trust this. ♫
[Sindarin] ♫ Estelio veleth. ♫
♫ [English]  ♫ Trust love. ♫
Where is she?
The woman who gave you that jewel.
Our time here is ending.
Arwen's time is ending.
Let her go.
Let her take the ship into the west.
Let her bear away her love
for you to the Undying Lands.
There it will be ever green.
But never more than memory.
I will not leave my daughter here to die.
- She stays because she still has hope.
- She stays for you.
She belongs with her people.
[Sindarin] Nach gwannatha sin?
[English] Are you going to leave in such way?
[Sindarin] Ma nathach hi gwannathach or minuial archened?
[English] You would depart after the stars fade - unseen?
[Sindarin] Ú-ethelithon.
[English] I will not return.
[Sindarin] Estelio guru lîn ne dagor.
[English] Trust in your skill in battle.
[Sindarin] Ethelithach.
[English] You will return.
[Sindarin]  Ú-bedin o gurth ne dagor.
[English] I don’t speak about death in battle.
[Sindarin] O man pedich?
[English] About what you speak?
[Sindarin] Edra le men, men na guil edwen...
[English] A path is opened for you, a path to another life...
[Sindarin] haer o auth a nîr a naeth.
[English] ...far from war and weeping and woe.
Why are you saying this?
I am mortal. You are Elf-kind.
It was a dream, Arwen.
Nothing more.
I don't believe you.
This belongs to you.
It was a gift.
Keep it.
My lord?
She is sailing to the Undying Lands
with all that is left of her kin.
What is it?
- Hama?
- I'm not sure.
Wargs!
A scout!
- What is it? What do you see?
- Warg! We're under attack!
Get them out of here!
All riders to the head of the column.
Come on. Get me up here. I'm a rider.
Come on!
You must lead the people to
Helm's Deep, and make haste.
- I can fight.
- No!
You must do this, for me.
Follow me!
- Forward. I mean, charge forward.
- Make for the lower ground!
- That's it! Go on!
- Stay together!
Bring your pretty face to my ax.
That one counts as mine!
Stinking creature.
Aragorn!
Aragorn?
Tell me what happened and I will ease your passing.
He's...
dead.
He took a little tumble off the cliff.
You lie.
Get the wounded on horses.
The wolves of Isengard will return.
Leave the dead.
Come.
- At last!
- Helm's Deep.
There it is, Helm's Deep.
We're safe!
We're safe, my lady.
Thank you.
- Mama!
- Eothain!
Freda!
- Where is the rest?
- This is all we could save, my lady.
Take it to the caves.
Make way for the king.
Make way for Theoden. Make way for the king.
So few. So few of you have returned.
Our people are safe.
We have paid for it with many lives.
My lady.
Lord Aragorn...
where is he?
He fell.
Draw all our forces behind the wall.
Bar the gate. And set a watch on the surround.
What of those who cannot fight,
my lord? The women and children?
Get them into the caves.
Saruman's arm will have grown long
indeed if he thinks he can reach us here.
Helm's Deep has one weakness.
Its outer wall is solid rock...
but for a small culvert at its base...
which is little more than a drain.
How? How can fire undo stone?
What kind of device could bring down the wall?
If the wall is breached, Helm's Deep will fall.
Even if it is breached, it would
take a number beyond reckoning...
thousands, to storm the Keep.
Tens of thousands.
But, my lord, there is no such force.
A new power is rising.
Its victory is at hand.
This night...
the land will be stained with the blood of Rohan!
March to Helm's Deep!
Leave none alive!
To war!
There will be no dawn for Men.
Look. There's smoke to the south.
There is always smoke rising...
from Isengard these days.
Isengard?
There was a time...
when Saruman would walk in my woods.
But now he has a mind of metal...
and wheels.
He no longer cares for growing things.
What is it?
It's Saruman's army.
The war has started.
May the grace of the Valar protect you.
Brego.
Arwen.
[Sindarin] Tollen, i lû.
[English] Come, it is time.
[Sindarin] I chair gwannar na Valannor. Si bado, no círar.
[English] The ships depart to Valinor. Now go, before they sail.
I have made my choice.
He is not coming back.
Why do you linger here when there is no hope?
There is still hope.
If Aragorn survives this war, you will still be parted.
If Sauron is defeated and Aragorn made king...
and all that you hope for comes true...
you will still have to taste
the bitterness of mortality.
Whether by the sword or the slow decay of time...
Aragorn will die.
And there will be no comfort for you...
no comfort to ease the pain of his passing.
He will come to death...
an image of the splendor of the kings of Men...
in glory undimmed before the breaking of the world.
But you, my daughter...
you will linger on in darkness and in doubt...
as nightfall in winter that comes without a star.
Here you will dwell...
bound to your grief under the fading trees...
until all the world is changed...
and the long years of your life are utterly spent.
Arwen.
There is nothing for you here...
only death.
[Sindarin] Ah im, ú-’erin veleth lîn?
[English] And I, I-have-not love your?
[Sindarin] Gerich veleth nîn, ada.
[English] You-have my love, father.
[Sindarin] I amar prestar aen.
[English] The world is changed.
[Sindarin] Han mathon ne nen.
[English] I feel it in the water.
[Sindarin] Han mathon ne chae.
[English] I feel it in the earth.
[Sindarin] A han noston ned ’wilith.
[English] I smell it in the air.
The power of the enemy is growing.
Sauron will use his puppet, Saruman...
to destroy the people of Rohan.
Isengard has been unleashed.
The Eye of Sauron now turns to Gondor...
the last free kingdom of Men.
His war on this country will come swiftly.
He senses the Ring is close.
The strength of the Ring-bearer is failing.
In his heart, Frodo begins to understand...
the quest will claim his life.
You know this.
You have foreseen it.
It is the risk we all took.
In the gathering dark, the
will of the Ring grows strong.
It works hard now to find its
way back into the hands of Men.
Men, who are so easily seduced by its power.
The young captain of Gondor
has but to extend his hand...
take the Ring for his own, and the world will fall.
It is close now.
So close to achieving its goal.
For Sauron will have dominion
over all life on this Earth...
even unto to the ending of the world.
The time of the Elves...
is over.
Do we leave Middle-earth to its fate?
Do we let them stand alone?
What news?
Our scouts report Saruman has attacked Rohan.
Theoden's people have fled to Helm's Deep.
But we must look to our own borders.
Faramir, Orcs are on the move.
Sauron is marshaling an army.
Easterlings and Southrons are at the Black Gate.
- How many?
- Some thousands. More come every day.
- Who's covering the river to the north?
- We pulled 500 men at Osgiliath.
If their city is attacked, we won't hold it.
Saruman attacks from Isengard.
Sauron from Mordor.
The fight will come to Men on both fronts.
Gondor is weak.
Sauron will strike us soon.
And he will strike hard.
He knows now we do not have the strength to repel him.
My men tell me that you are Orc spies.
Spies? Now wait just a minute.
Well, if you're not spies, then who are you?
Speak.
We are Hobbits of the Shire.
Frodo Baggins is my name, and this is Samwise Gamgee.
Your bodyguard?
His gardener.
And where is your skulking friend?
That gangrel creature.
He had an ill-favored look.
There was no other.
We set out from Rivendell with seven companions.
One we lost in Moria...
two were my kin...
a Dwarf there was also. And an Elf and two Men.
Aragorn, son of Arathorn, and Boromir of Gondor.
You're a friend of Boromir?
Yes.
For my part.
It will grieve you then to learn that he is dead.
Dead?
How? When?
As one of his companions, I'd hoped you would tell me.
If something has happened to
Boromir, we would have you tell us.
His horn washed up upon the
riverbank, about six days past.
It was cloven in two.
But more than this, I know it in my heart.
He was my brother.
Boromir!
This city was once the jewel of our kingdom.
A place of light and beauty and music.
And so it shall be once more!
Let the armies of Mordor know this:
Never again will the land of
my people fall into enemy hands.
This city of Osgiliath has been reclaimed for Gondor!
- For Gondor!
Good speech. Nice and short.
Leaves more time for drinking!
Break out the ale! These men are thirsty!
Remember today, little brother.
Today, life is good.
What?
He's here.
One moment of peace, can he not give us that?
Where is he?
Where is Gondor's finest? Where's my first-born?
Father!
They say you vanquished the
enemy almost single-handedly.
They exaggerate. The victory belongs to Faramir also.
But for Faramir, this city would still be standing.
Were you not entrusted to protect it?
I would have done, but our numbers were too few.
Oh, too few.
You let the enemy walk in and take it on a whim.
Always you cast a poor reflection on me.
That is not my intent.
You give him no credit, and
yet he tries to do your will.
- He loves you, Father.
- Do not trouble me with Faramir...
I know his uses, and they are few.
We have more urgent things to speak of.
Elrond of Rivendell has called a meeting.
He will not say why, but I have guessed its purpose.
It is rumored that the weapon
of the enemy has been found.
The One Ring.
- Isildur's Bane.
- It has fallen into the hands of the Elves.
Everyone will try to claim it: Men, Dwarves, wizards.
We cannot let that happen.
This thing must come to Gondor.
- Gondor.
- It's dangerous, I know.
Ever the Ring will seek to
corrupt the hearts of lesser Men.
But you, you are strong. And our need is great.
It is our blood which is being
spilled, our people who are dying.
Sauron is biding his time. He's massing fresh armies.
He will return.
And when he does, we will be powerless to stop him.
You must go.
Bring me back this mighty gift.
No. My place is here with my people. Not in Rivendell.
- Would you deny your own father?
- If there is need to go to Rivendell...
- send me in his stead.
- You?
Oh, I see.
A chance for Faramir, captain
of Gondor, to show his quality.
I think not.
I trust this mission only to your brother.
The one who will not fail me.
Remember today, little brother.
Captain Faramir!
We found the third one.
You must come with me. Now.
Down there.
To enter the Forbidden Pool bears the penalty of death.
They wait for my command.
Shall I shoot?
The rock and pool Is nice and cool
So juicy sweet
Our only wish To catch a fish
Wait.
This creature is bound to me.
And I to him.
He is our guide.
Please...
let me go down to him.
Smeagol.
Master is here.
Come, Smeagol.
Trust master. Come.
We must go now?
Smeagol, you must trust master.
Follow me. Come on.
Come.
Come, Smeagol.
Nice Smeagol. That's it.
Come on.
Don't hurt him!
Smeagol, don't struggle. Smeagol, listen to me.
Master!
Why does it cry, Smeagol?
Cruel Men hurts us.
Master tricksed us.
Of course he did.
I told you he was tricksy.
I told you he was false.
Master is our friend.
Our friend.
Master betrayed us.
No. Not its business.
Leave us alone!
Filthy little Hobbitses!
They stole it from us!
No. No.
What did they steal?
My precious!
We have to get out of here.
You go. Go, now.
You can do it.
Use the Ring, Mr. Frodo.
Just this once.
Put it on.
Disappear.
I can't.
You were right, Sam.
You tried to tell me but...
I'm sorry.
The Ring's taking me, Sam.
If I put it on...
he'll find me.
He'll see.
Mr. Frodo...
So this is the answer to all the riddles.
Here in the Wild I have you...
two Halflings...
and a host of men at my call.
The Ring of Power within my grasp.
A chance for Faramir, captain of Gondor...
to show his quality.
No!
Stop it!
Leave him alone.
Don't you understand?
He's got to destroy it!
That's where we're going, into Mordor.
To the Mountain of Fire!
Osgiliath is under attack.
They call for reinforcements.
Please. It's such a burden.
Will you not help him?
Captain?
Prepare to leave.
The Ring will go to Gondor.
[Sindarin] Mae carnen, Brego, mellon nîn.
[English] Well done, Brego, my friend.
- He's alive!
- Where is he? Where is he?
Get out of the way! I'm going to kill him!
You are the luckiest, the canniest...
and the most reckless man I ever knew.
Bless you, laddie.
Gimli, where is the king?
[Sindarin] Le abdollen.
[English] You’re late.
You look terrible.
[Sindarin] Hannon le.
[English] Thank you.
A great host, you say?
- All Isengard is emptied.
- How many?
Ten thousand strong at least.
Ten thousand?
It is an army bred for a single purpose:
To destroy the world of Men.
They will be here by nightfall.
Let them come!
I want every man and strong lad able to bear arms...
to be ready for battle by nightfall.
We will cover the causeway and the gate from above.
No army has ever breached the Deeping Wall...
or set foot inside the Hornburg!
This is no rabble of mindless Orcs.
These are Uruk-hai.
Their armor is thick and their shields broad.
I have fought many wars, Master Dwarf.
I know how to defend my own keep.
They will break upon this fortress like water on rock.
Saruman's hordes will pillage
and burn. We've seen it before.
Crops can be resown...
homes rebuilt.
Within these walls...
we will outlast them.
They do not come to destroy Rohan's crops or villages.
They come to destroy its people...
down to the last child.
What would you have me do?
Look at my men.
Their courage hangs by a thread.
If this is to be our end, then I
would have them make such an end...
as to be worthy of remembrance.
Send out riders, my lord.
You must call for aid.
And who will come?
Elves?
Dwarves?
We are not so lucky in our friends as you.
The old alliances are dead.
- Gondor will answer.
- Gondor?!
Where was Gondor when the Westfold fell?!
Where was Gondor when our enemies closed in around us?!
Where was Gon...?
No, my Lord Aragorn...
we are alone.
Get the women and children into the caves.
We need more time to lay provisions...
There is no time. War is upon us.
Secure the gate.
We Ents have not troubled...
about the wars of Men and wizards...
for a very long time.
But now, something is about to happen...
that has not happened...
for an age.
Entmoot.
What's that?
'Tis a gathering.
A gathering of what?
Beech. Oak.
Chestnut. Ash.
Good. Good. Good.
Many have come.
Now we must decide if the Ents...
will go to war.
Move back! Move to the caves!
Come on, people! Quickly, now!
We'll place the reserves along the wall.
They can support the archers from above the gate.
Aragorn, you must rest.
You're no use to us half alive.
Aragorn!
I'm to be sent with the women into the caves.
That is an honorable charge.
To mind the children, to find food
and bedding when the men return.
What renown is there in that?
My lady, a time may come for valor without renown.
Who then will your people look to in the last defense?
- Let me stand at your side.
- It is not in my power to command it.
You do not command the others to stay!
They fight beside you because
they would not be parted from you.
Because they love you.
I'm sorry.
Farmers, farriers, stable boys.
These are no soldiers.
- Most have seen too many winters.
- Or too few.
Look at them. They're frightened.
I can see it in their eyes.
[Sindarin] Boe a hyn...
[English] And they should be...
[Sindarin] Neled herain... dan caer menig.
[English] Three hundred... against ten thousand.
[Sindarin] Si, beriathar hyn ammaeg na ned Edoras.
[English] Here they-will-defend them-selves sharper than at Edoras.
[Sindarin] Aragorn, nedin dagor hen ú-’erir ortheri.
[English] Aragorn, in this battle they can not win.
[Sindarin] Natha daged dhaer
[English] It will be great slaying.
Then I shall die as one of them!
Let him go, lad.
Let him be.
Every villager able to wield a
sword has been sent to the armory.
My lord?
Who am I, Gamling?
You are our king, sire.
And do you trust your king?
Your men, my lord...
will follow you to whatever end.
To whatever end.
Where is the horse and the rider?
Where is the horn that was blowing?
They have passed like rain on the mountains.
Like wind in the meadow.
The days have gone down in the West...
behind the hills...
into Shadow.
How did it come to this?
It's been going for hours.
They must have decided something by now.
Decided? No.
We only just finished saying...
good morning.
But it's nighttime already.
You can't take forever.
Don't be hasty.
We're running out of time!
Move! Move to the outer wall.
Give me your sword.
What is your name?
Haleth, son of Hama, my lord.
The men are saying we will not live out the night.
They say that it is hopeless.
This is a good sword.
Haleth, son of Hama...
there is always hope.
We have trusted you this far.
You have not led us astray.
Forgive me.
I was wrong to despair.
[Sindarin] Ú-moe edaved, Legolas
[English] There is nothing to forgive, Legolas.
We had time, I'd get this adjusted.
It's a little tight across the chest.
That is no Orc horn.
Send for the king.
- Open the gate!
- Open up the gate!
How is this possible?
I bring word from Elrond of Rivendell.
An alliance once existed between Elves and Men.
Long ago we fought and died together.
We come to honor that allegiance.
[Sindarin] Mae govannen, Haldir.
[English] Well-met, Haldir.
You are most welcome.
We are proud to fight alongside Men once more.
You could have picked a better spot.
Well, lad, whatever luck you live
by, let's hope it lasts the night.
Your friends are with you, Aragorn.
Let's hope they last the night.
[Sindarin] A Eruchîn, ú-dano i faelas a hyn...
[English] O Children-of-Eru, don’t show mercy to them...
[Sindarin] ...an uben tanatha le faelas!
[English] ...for nobody will show you mercy!
- What's happening out there?
- Shall I describe it to you?
Or would you like me to find you a box?
[Sindarin] Dartho!
[English] Hold!
So it begins.
[Sindarin] Tangado a chadad!
[English] Prepare to fire!
[Sindarin] Faeg i-varv dîn na lanc...
[English] Their armour is poor below the neck...
[Sindarin] ...a nu ranc!
[English] ...and under arm!
[Sindarin] Hado i philinn!
[English] Release the arrows!
Did they hit anything?
Give them a volley.
- Fire!
Send them to me! Come on!
[Sindarin] Pendraith!
[English] Ladders!
Good!
Swords! Swords!
Legolas! Two already!
I'm on 17!
I'll have no pointy-ear outscoring me!
Nineteen!
Merry.
We have just agreed.
Yes?
I have told your names to the Entmoot...
and we have agreed...
you are not Orcs.
Well, that's good news.
And what about Saruman? Have
you come to a decision about him?
Now, don't be hasty, Master Meriadoc.
Hasty?
Our friends are out there.
They need our help. They cannot
fight this war on their own.
War? Yes.
It affects us all.
Tree, root and twig.
But you must understand, young Hobbit...
it takes a long time...
to say anything in Old Entish...
and we never say anything...
unless it is worth taking...
a long time to say.
Seventeen! Eighteen!
Nineteen!
Twenty!
Twenty-one!
Causeway!
[Sindarin] Na fennas!
[English] To gateway!
[Sindarin] Hado ribed! Hado!
[English] Hurl to flow! Hurl!
Is this it?
Is this is all you can conjure, Saruman?
[Sindarin] Togo hon dad, Legolas!
[English] Bring him down, Legolas!
[Sindarin] Dago hon!
[English] Kill him!
Brace the gate!
Hold them! Stand firm!
Aragorn!
Gimli!
[Sindarin] Hado i philinn!
[English] Release the arrows!
[Sindarin] Herio!
[English] Charge!
The Ents cannot hold back this storm.
We must weather such things as we have always done.
How can that be your decision?!
This is not our war.
But you're part of this world!
Aren't you?!
You must help. Please.
You must do something.
You are young and brave, Master Merry.
But your part in this tale is over.
Go back to your home.
Maybe Treebeard's right.
We don't belong here, Merry.
It's too big for us.
What can we do in the end?
We've got the Shire.
Maybe we should go home.
The fires of Isengard will spread...
and the woods of Tuckborough and Buckland will burn.
And...
And all that was once green and
good in this world will be gone.
There won't be a Shire, Pippin.
Aragorn!
Fall back to the Keep!
Get your men out of there!
[Sindarin] Nan barad!
[English] To tower!
Haldir!
[Sindarin] Nan barad!
[English] To tower!
What are you doing? What are you stopping for?
Haldir!
Brace the gate!
Hold them!
To the gate. Draw your swords!
Make way!
We can't hold much longer!
- Hold them!
- How long do you need?
As long as you can give me.
Gimli!
Timbers!
Brace the gate!
Come on. We can take them.
It's a long way.
Toss me.
- What?
- I cannot jump the distance!
You'll have to toss me!
Don't tell the Elf.
Not a word.
Shore up the door!
- Make way!
- Follow me to the barricade.
Watch our backs!
- Throw another one over here!
- Higher!
Hold fast the gate!
Gimli! Aragorn! Get out of there!
Aragorn!
Pull everybody back.
Pull them back.
Fall back!
They have broken through!
The castle is breached. Retreat!
- Fall back!
- Retreat!
Hurry! Inside. Get them inside!
Into the Keep!
I will leave you at the western borders of the forest.
You can make your way north
to your homeland from there.
Wait! Stop!
Stop!
Turn around.
- Turn around. Take us south.
- South?
But that will lead you past Isengard.
Yes. Exactly.
If we go south, we can slip past Saruman unnoticed.
The closer we are to danger,
the farther we are from harm.
It's the last thing he'll expect.
That doesn't make sense to me.
But then...
you are very small.
Perhaps you're right.
South it is, then.
Hold on, little Shirelings.
I always like going south.
Somehow it feels like going downhill.
Are you mad? We'll be caught.
No, we won't.
Not this time.
Look!
Osgiliath burns!
Mordor has come.
The Ring will not save Gondor.
It has only the power to destroy.
Please...
let me go.
Hurry.
Faramir!
You must let me go!
And those little family of field mice...
that climb up sometimes, and they tickle me awfully.
They're always trying to get somewhere where they...
Many of these trees were my friends.
Creatures I had known from nut and acorn.
I'm sorry, Treebeard.
They had voices of their own.
Saruman.
A wizard should know better!
There is no curse in Elvish...
Entish or the tongues of Men...
for this treachery.
Look! The trees! They're moving!
Where are they going?
They have business with the Orcs.
My business is with Isengard tonight...
with rock and stone.
Yes.
Come, my friends.
The Ents are going to war.
It is likely...
that we go to our doom.
Last march...
of the Ents.
Faramir! Orcs have taken the eastern
shore. Their numbers are too great.
By nightfall we will be overrun.
Mr. Frodo?
It's calling to him, Sam. His Eye is almost on me.
Hold on, Mr. Frodo. You'll be all right.
Take them to my father.
Tell him Faramir sends a mighty gift.
A weapon that will change our fortunes in this war.
Do you want to know what happened to Boromir?
You want to know why your brother died?
He tried to take the Ring from Frodo
after swearing an oath to protect him!
He tried to kill him!
The Ring drove your brother mad!
Watch out!
Mr. Frodo?
They're here.
They've come.
Nazgul!
Stay here. Keep out of sight.
Take cover!
The fortress is taken.
It is over.
You said this fortress would never
fall while your men defend it.
They still defend it. They have died defending it.
They're breaking in!
They're past the door!
Is there no other way for the women
and children to get out of the caves?
Is there no other way?
There is one passage. It leads into the mountains.
But they will not get far. The Uruk-hai are too many.
Tell the women and children
to make for the mountain pass.
- And barricade the entrance!
- So much death.
What can Men do against such reckless hate?
Ride out with me.
Ride out and meet them.
For death and glory.
For Rohan.
For your people.
The sun is rising.
Look to my coming at first light on the fifth day.
At dawn...
look to the east.
Yes.
The horn of Helm Hammerhand...
shall sound in the Deep...
one last time.
Yes!
Let this be the hour when we draw swords together.
Fell deeds, awake.
Now for wrath...
now for ruin and a red dawn.
[Rohirric] Forð Eorlingas!
[English] Forth Eorlingas!
Gandalf.
Theoden King stands alone.
Not alone.
Rohirrim!
Eomer.
To the king!
Yes!
A hit. A fine hit.
Break the dam!
Release the river!
Pippin! Hold on!
Hold on, little Hobbits.
What are you doing?
Where are you going?
It's me.
It's your Sam.
Don't you know your Sam?
I can't do this, Sam.
I know.
It's all wrong.
By rights, we shouldn't even be here.
But we are.
It's like in the great stories, Mr. Frodo.
The ones that really mattered.
Full of darkness and danger they were.
And sometimes you didn't want to know the end...
because how could the end be happy?
How could the world go back to the way it was...
when so much bad had happened?
Victory!
We have victory!
But in the end, it's only a passing thing...
this shadow.
Even darkness must pass.
A new day will come.
And when the sun shines, it will shine out the clearer.
Those were the stories that stayed with you...
that meant something.
Even if you were too small to understand why.
But I think, Mr. Frodo, I do understand.
I know now.
Folk in those stories...
had lots of chances of turning back, only they didn't.
They kept going...
because they were holding on to something.
What are we holding on to, Sam?
That there's some good in this world, Mr. Frodo.
And it's worth fighting for.
I think at last we understand
one another, Frodo Baggins.
You know the laws of our
country, the laws of your father.
If you let them go, your life will be forfeit.
Then it is forfeit.
Release them.
Stay out of the forest!
Keep away from the trees!
Final count...
- 42.
- 42?
That's not bad for a pointy-eared Elvish princeling.
I myself am sitting pretty on 43.
- 43.
- He was already dead.
- He was twitching.
- He was twitching...
because he's got my ax embedded in his nervous system!
- He doesn't look too happy, does he?
- Not too happy at all, Merry.
Still, I suppose the view would
be quite nice from up there.
Oh, yes. It's a quality establishment.
I hear the staff are very good.
- What are you doing?
- Nothing.
- The world's back to normal, that's all.
- No, it isn't.
I'm starving.
Good luck trying to find something decent around here.
Probably dead rats and moldy bread.
Saruman's storeroom!
I don't believe it.
It can't be.
- It is!
- Longbottom Leaf.
The finest pipe-weed in South Farthing.
It's perfect. One barrel each.
Wait.
Do you think we should share it with Treebeard?
Share it?
No. No.
Dead plant and all that.
Don't think he'd understand.
Could be a distant relative.
I get it.
Don't be hasty.
Exactly.
Bar-hrum.
This is the old sewer.
Runs right under the river
through to the edge of the city.
You'll find cover in the woods there.
Captain Faramir...
you have shown your quality, sir.
The very highest.
The Shire must truly be a great realm, Master Gamgee...
where gardeners are held in high honor.
What road will you take once you reach the woods?
Gollum says there's a path...
near Minas Morgul that climbs up into the mountains.
Cirith Ungol?
- Is that its name?
- No.
No!
- Yes.
- Frodo...
they say a dark terror dwells
in the passes above Minas Morgul.
- You cannot go that way.
- It is the only way.
Master says we must go to Mordor, so we must try.
I must.
Go, Frodo. Go with the goodwill of all Men.
Thank you.
May death find you quickly if you bring them to harm.
Come on, keep up.
Mr. Frodo didn't mean for them Rangers to hurt you.
You know that, don't you?
He was trying to save you, see?
Save me?
So there's no hard feelings.
- Forgive and forget.
- No, no, no hard feelings.
Gollum, Gollum.
Yes, master.
- Nice Hobbits.
- Very decent of you.
Very decent, indeed, Gollum.
Sauron's wrath will be terrible, his retribution swift.
The battle for Helm's Deep is over.
The battle for Middle-earth is about to begin.
All our hopes now lie with two little Hobbits...
somewhere in the wilderness.
I wonder if we'll ever be put into songs or tales.
What?
I wonder if people will ever say,
"Let's hear about Frodo and the Ring."
And they'll say, "Yes! That's
one of my favorite stories."
"Frodo was really courageous, wasn't he, Dad?"
"Yes, my boy.
The most famousest of Hobbits.
And that's saying a lot."
Well, you've left out one of the chief characters:
"Samwise the Brave."
I want to hear more about Sam.
Frodo wouldn't have got far without Sam.
Now, Mr. Frodo, you shouldn't
make fun. I was being serious.
So was I.
"Samwise the Brave."
Smeagol?
We're not going to wait for you. Come on.
Master.
Master looks after us.
Master wouldn't hurt us.
Master broke his promise.
Don't ask Smeagol.
Poor, poor Smeagol.
Master betrayed us.
Wicked. Tricksy. False.
We ought to wring his filthy little neck.
Kill him! Kill him!
Kill them both!
And then we take the precious...
and we be the master!
But the fat Hobbit, he knows.
Eyes always watching.
Then we stabs them out.
Put out his eyeses and make him crawl.
Yes. Yes. Yes.
Kill them both.
Yes. No! No!
It's too risky. It's too risky.
Where is he? Where has he gone?
- Hey, Gollum! Where are you?
- Smeagol?
We could let her do it.
Yes. She could do it.
Yes, precious, she could.
And then we takes it once they're dead.
Once they're dead.
Come on, Hobbits. Long ways to go yet.
Smeagol will show you the way.
Follow me.